So what we're going to do today is
figuring out in terms of the issue of אונאה Ona'ah and how
much and how to determine it and what really what we had
a whole discussion about how you define a sixth, but the real
focus now is on the three stages of אונאה. Ona'ah. What happens
at each stage and what the sort of time period is. So
basically the גמרא Gemara has read in the משנה, Mishnah, not clear
that it's exactly פשט Pshat of the משנה, Mishnah, but that there
are three stages, okay? Under a sixth it's considered מחילה. Mechila. One
way of understanding that is basically just like that's a tolerable, you
know, sort of range within the standard going price. Exactly a sixth
is called אונאה. Ona'ah. The general assumption about אונאה Ona'ah is that
you have a choice, right? And the choice is either or the
person cheated has a choice, either ביטול Bittul or you know you
get your overpay back. Overpay back. Okay, that's the choice. And more
than a sixth, and I'm making a sixth as a range so
it a stands out and b so that also because according to
שמואל Shmuel there is a range. And more than a sixth is
ביטול מקח, Bittul Mekach, okay? Which either side can retract, which as
we pointed out is a little ironic, you know, I'll just overcharge
the guy a little more as a seller and then I'll have
more options available to me. So there's some discussion about that, but
anyway that's the point. That's so grossly overcharged, it's ביטול מקח. Bittul
Mekach. All right, now the גמרא's Gemara point now the גמרא, Gemara,
the משנה Mishnah says that when it is אונאה Ona'ah you have
you lose your right for redress if you've had a chance to
show it to friends or relatives or you know within the normal
amount of time and you didn't do anything about it. Then you
sort of forgo your rights. So the principle of עד שיראה Ad
Sheyeira is set explicitly in the משנה Mishnah by the case of
אונאה, Ona'ah, the middle case. The question the גמרא Gemara is focusing
on is, does that also true about מחילה Mechila and is that
also true about ביטול Bittul well we're going to get to the
second part ביטול מקח. Bittul Mekach. Okay? Do those things happen automatic
or those things also you know and you can't retract whatever or
do those things also you know you have a time clock on
them. Okay? So do we say that for example if it was
if it was in this area, all right, the person actually can
get his money back if he comes back in a short period
of time. It's only if he waits beyond a certain amount of
time is it a מחילה. Mechila. Okay? Right, well that's another way
of saying it too, correct. Okay, so that's the question. Certainly though
the אונאה Ona'ah has a clock on it, it's only good עד
שיראה. Ad Sheyeira. The question is, is the מחילה Mechila automatic or
is the מחילה Mechila only after עד שיראה? Ad Sheyeira? Is the
ביטול Bittul and we'll see a similar question by the ביטול מקח.
Bittul Mekach. That is the key question that's focusing our גמרא Gemara
from yesterday and that we have to wrap up. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara wants to answer this by saying by looking at
what the story would be with רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Okay, because
according to רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said, if
you remember and this is going to sort of the גמרא's Gemara
going to focus whatever focus on this sort of reality that the
merchants first liked רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and then they didn't. First
he said no, no, you don't have a sixth, you have up
to a third. Okay? And then they and then they were all
very happy and they wanted to be a רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
kind. And then he said, but I'm giving people a whole day,
and then they flipped back. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara first says,
well you know assuming that a third meant the same under a
third meant the same as under a sixth, so that would be
for him he would be saying it's all מחילה. Mechila. So if
מחילה Mechila is automatic, right, and it's not only after you pass
a certain time, then a day having a day means only at
the third thing, like at the אונאה Ona'ah stage
up here at a third, right?
That's what sort of so that's when he's limiting it by a
day. But if מחילה Mechila is automatic, you totally want to stay
on this side of the board, right? You want the מחילה Mechila
to be automatic. So this proves that מחילה Mechila is not automatic.
Okay, that מחילה Mechila has a clock too. So when he changed
the clock they wanted to flip the side. Because if it's okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says no, maybe מחילה Mechila is automatic, but
he limits his מחילה Mechila to the same scenarios the Rabbis limit
מחילה Mechila to. What he is doing is he is making what
the Rabbis have as their little one-sixth stage, okay, you know, one-sixth
אונאה, Ona'ah, he is making like all of this the אונאה. Ona'ah.
Okay, this all is what the one-sixth is for the רבנן. Rabbanan.
All right, that's what the גמרא Gemara said. And therefore they gave
him עד שיראה. Ad Sheyeira. All right, so once so you have
three hours, let's say. Okay? And once three hours passes, you know
okay, and he said well anyway they so the first was that
they said more than a sixth is ביטול מקח. Bittul Mekach. He
said no, no, no, I give you up to a third. We're
going to just work with the presumption here that they would rather
be called אונאה ona'ah than ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, okay, for whatever.
All right, so they say yay, it's only going to be אונאה,
ona'ah, it won't be ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. We like this, okay?
They switched over. Then he said, "no, but I'm going to give
people a whole day
and after, you know, so they say you have a whole day
to get your money back or to retract the sale." And they
say, "Well, we'd rather be over here that people only have a
few hours and afterwards they're stuck with it, okay, than giving people
a whole day." So that explains why they switched back. Is that
clear? That's sort of where we got up to, all right? So
מחילה, mechilah, this מחילה mechilah will be automatic. So you have to
have these as the same or else they wouldn't want to switch.
אונאה ona'ah is the thing that has the clock, okay? So initially
they thought it would be עד שיראה, ad sheyireh, so they say
we'd rather be on this side of the board, have it אונאה
ona'ah rather than ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. And then he says, "actually,
I'm going to give them כל היום, kol hayom, okay, to get
their money back or to be מבטל mevatel the sale." And they
say, "oh, well, we'd rather the sale be as final and as
quickly as possible, we'd rather be back onto this side of the
board where you only has a few hours." All right. Yes.
What was the לשון lashon for so to speak all day? עד
שיראה ad sheyireh is כל היום. kol hayom. A כל היום, kol
hayom, that's what it says, you couldn't find
it?
Okay, so גמרא gemara says like this. Okay, so let's read that.
Okay, we'll pick it up again from four lines from the top.
This is the משנה mishnah over here.
Okay, we're going to pick it up again from four lines from
the
top, and just stay with me because we got to get through
this. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this: מי סברת פחות
משליש רבי טרפון כפחות משתות רבנן דמי Mi savrat pachos mishlish Rabbi
Tarfon kefachos mishtus rabanan dami? No, it's not that all of this
would be מחילה. mechilah. לא משתות עד שליש רבי טרפון כשתות עצמה
לרבנן דמי. Lo mishtus ad shlish Rabbi Tarfon keshtus atzmah lerabanan dami.
From a third to a sixth is all אונאה ona'ah just like
this sixth is אונאה. ona'ah. So it's possible מחילה mechilah is automatic.
But they still would rather switch back because up here we're not
dealing with מחילה. mechilah. איהכי במאי שמחו מעיקרא Ei hachi bemai samchu
me'ikara?
Now, why were they happy to go to call it אונאה? ona'ah?
Right? Because if you think about it, I just said except for
faith that they'd rather be אונאה ona'ah than ביטול מקח. bitul mekach.
But the גמרא's gemara's saying, yeah, why would you rather have it
as אונאה ona'ah than ביטול מקח? bitul mekach? אונאה ona'ah is they
get their money back or they can be מבטל mevatel it. ביטול
מקח bitul mekach is ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. Doesn't seem to me
like it really matters much from the seller's perspective whether you call
it אונאה ona'ah or ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, right? So why did...
so that doesn't make sense. Okay, so you're telling me he expanded
that, but still who cares? Right? Why should they prefer אונאה ona'ah
to ביטול מקח? bitul mekach? So תפשוט tifshot we should conclude that
if initially they did prefer this, why did they prefer that? דביטול
מקח לרבנן לעולם חוזר, Debitul mekach lerabanan le'olam chozer, that when you're
in this ביטול מקח bitul mekach category, you have לעולם, le'olam, you
can always be מבטל mevatel it. So now we understand. בא רבי
טרפון Ba Rabbi Tarfon and Rabbi Tarfon said, "I am going to
consider all this space to be אונאה." ona'ah. Okay, and then they
figured, great, we'd much rather be here, give the buyer an extra
option he can get his overpay back, but still there's a clock
associated with it. You know, first they thought it was עד שיראה,
ad sheyireh, then it became כל היום. kol hayom. But whatever it
is, there's a time limit. We'd much rather be here with a
time limit, right, than be over here where this entire range, right,
say that you can always get a refund. That makes a lot
of sense.
It's a crazy business model.
I don't know, anyway, that makes a lot of sense. I would
totally
agree. I do not want to be Land's End that you can
always go ahead and get a refund 20 years later. I know
people that buy from Land's End, they like wear it out 10
years later, they return it, get their money back. Anyway, fine. I
would much rather be here. So now we get it, they'd much
rather be here because this is
לעולם. le'olam. Okay. ביטול מקח לרבנן לעולם חוזר. Bitul mekach lerabanan le'olam
chozer. דכיון דאמר להו רבי טרפון הוי אונאה, Dekivan de'amar lehu Rabbi
Tarfon havei ona'ah, I'm going to call it אונאה ona'ah and remember
אונאה ona'ah is always the thing with the clock associated with it.
We don't know about the clock here, but we know that אונאה
ona'ah is always the thing with the clock. So שמחו, samchu, then
they're happy, because now it's a limited time period that they can,
all right? And so that makes a lot of sense. What doesn't
make sense is why they would switch back when he says כל
היום. kol hayom. Because still, last check, כל היום kol hayom is
a shorter amount of time than לעולם, le'olam, okay? So the גמרא
gemara says כי אמר להו כל היום חזרו. Ki amar lehu kol
hayom hazru. Now we get why when he said כל היום kol
hayom they went back. Now that's hard to understand and I can't
belabor it because that's why you have a huge תוספות Tosafos because
this is a hard גמרא gemara to understand. But I'll just tell
you in one second, רש"י Rashi says the point is this: כל
היום, kol hayom, רש"י Rashi says, is pretty close to לעולם le'olam
in the sense that, you know, anybody who's going to return an
object, right, if you give them the whole day, then the amount
of extra people that will return the object if you give them
forever as opposed to the whole day is a small number of
people. Okay? The difference between three hours and the whole day, you're
going to get a lot more people asking for refunds. Okay, that's
just what רש"י Rashi says, we'll take that on faith. So now
you said כל היום... kol hayom... So it's not such a big
difference, and therefore they'd rather be on this side, okay, because you
know at least when you're at the sixth level, there is a
difference. This is only a few hours and that's a whole day.
So we can sort of understand why initially they liked this, okay,
because you'd rather have it limited than being לעולם, la'olam, but כל
היום kol hayom
effectively is pretty close to, neutralizes that difference, and therefore they'd rather
be over here where at least in some areas it's very limited.
I know, אונאה ona'ah does have more
options for, I know אונאה ona'ah does have more options for, so
that's why they'd prefer maybe
to
go, no, no, actually, actually אונאה ona'ah
gives,
it gives, it gives the buyer more options, so that's
why they'd prefer maybe to go, the seller
would prefer to go over to, oh, because you, oh, I see,
that's an interesting point. You're saying that ביטול מקח bitul mekach besides
that you have more time, but anyway, but the guy can't ask
for his overpay back, maybe. Okay, so anyway, that's the logic. At
least we basically get it. All right? You started here that you'd
rather be limited than you'd be לעולם. la'olam. He tells them כל
היום, kol hayom, it mostly neutralizes that difference, and then they'd rather
be at this side because at least here you've got a limited
clock. That makes sense. Okay. No, I can't. We gotta finish this
thought. Okay. דאי סלקא דעתך דביטול מקח לרבנן בכדי שיראה לתגר או
לקרובו, de'i salka da'atach debitul mekach lerabanan bichedei sheyera'eh letagar o likrovo,
but if you say, because again, now we're focusing on whether מחילה
mechilah is automatic. The flip of מחילה mechilah being automatic is that
ביטול מקח bitul mekach is לעולם. la'olam. When one is automatic, one
is forever. This is definitely בכדי שיראה. bichedei sheyera'eh. But here the
גמרא Gemara says this reading will not work if ביטול מקח bitul
mekach is also עד שיראה. ad sheyera'eh. Why? Because if ביטול מקח
bitul mekach is עד שיראה ad sheyera'eh and אונאה ona'ah is עד
שיראה, ad sheyera'eh, why are you so happy that you're calling it
אונאה ona'ah rather than ביטול מקח? bitul mekach? Right? As we said
before, if
anything, you know, you know אונאה ona'ah gives the buyer more options.
So, so if this is עד שיראה, ad sheyera'eh, it does, it
makes no sense why they prefer to be on this side of
the board. All right? Okay. כי אמר להו כל היום, דאי סלקא
דעתך דביטול מקח לרבנן בכדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו, ki amar lehu
kol hayom, de'i salka da'atach debitul mekach lerabanan bichedei sheyera'eh letagar o
likrovo, במאי סמכו? bemai samchu? What would they be happy about? סמכו
בפשיטות עצמה samchu bifshitus atzmah דרבי טרפון מחילה ולרבנן אונאה. deRabbi Tarfon
mechilah ulerabanan ona'ah. Ah, so now what we're going to do is
change what we assumed, and here's going to be the difference. The
line for מחילה mechilah is not going to be up to a
sixth, the line for מחילה mechilah is going to include a sixth.
So what they were happy about is true. When you're up here,
okay, this they felt אונאה, ona'ah, ביטול מקח bitul mekach is all
בכדי שיראה. bichedei sheyera'eh. There's no reason to prefer to be on
this side of the board, might as well just be ביטול מקח
בכדי שיראה. bitul mekach bichedei sheyera'eh. And when you're down here, מחילה
mechilah is automatic, there's no preference. But at exactly a שיתות, shashtos,
right? No, a שיתות, shashtos, right, because רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is
the question is how does he draw the line differently? At exactly
a שיתות, shashtos, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is defining that as מחילה
mechilah and for לרבנן lerabanan that's where אונאה ona'ah starts, okay? So
that's a very complicated, none of that is in the משנה, Mishna,
but that's what we're going to assert. Okay. So it's possible they
preferred to be here because they wanted the sixth to be
מחילה mechilah and then he said, ah, but I'm going to give
them up here, you know, I'm going to give them the whole
day. And they said, oh, you're giving them the whole day? When
you get up here, we'd rather be at this side where they
only have עד שיראה. ad sheyera'eh. All right. Fine. That's the way
it works. Okay. Okay, now, fine. So we're done with that. We
have basically gone to a very complicated read of the whole thing.
It would, and by making this whole thing, it's possible to say
מחילה mechilah was automatic. We don't know. The easier read is that
מחילה mechilah was עד שיראה. ad sheyera'eh. But nevertheless, we've structured it
that it's possible that מחילה mechilah is automatic. Now we're going to
ask the implicitly, the, what we're going to focus on is what
we were, is what was part of the discussion before. Is מחילה
mechilah one is automatic or עד שיראה? ad sheyera'eh? The other is
ביטול מקח לעולם bitul mekach la'olam or עד שיראה? ad sheyera'eh? So
איבעיא להו. iba'ya lehu. They asked the following question. ביטול מקח לרבנן,
לעולם
חוזר או דילמא בכדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו? bitul mekach lerabanan, la'olam
chozer o dilma bichedei sheyera'eh letagar o likrovo? Which is part of
what we folded into the previous conversation. Okay. We know אונאה ona'ah
is עד שיראה. ad sheyera'eh. First the question was, is מחילה mechilah
automatic? And the other question is, is ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, is
that לעולם la'olam or also if you waited a certain period of
time you've waived your rights for ביטול מקח? bitul mekach? ואם תמצא
לומר בכדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו, ve'im timtza lomar bichedei sheyera'eh letagar
o likrovo,
now, if we would say that it would be בכדי שיראה, bichedei
sheyera'eh, before we get to answering that question, we have to understand
well then how is it different? Okay, here you have until שיראה
sheyera'eh and then it's final. Here you have until שיראה sheyera'eh and
then it's final. What difference does it make whether you call it
אונאה ona'ah or ביטול מקח? bitul mekach? So there's a big difference.
Okay. מאי איכא, mai ika, right?
בין שיתות ליתירה אשיתות? bein shashtos liyesera ashashtos? איכא. ika. דאילו שיתות
משנתאנה חוזר. de'ilu shashtos mishenisna'eh chozer. If it was exactly a sixth,
then the, you know, this is the irony of it, then the
right is
only in the hand of the cheated party. ואילו יתירה אשיתות שניהם
חוזרים. ve'ilu yesera ashashtos sheneihem chozrim. When it's more, both return. I
mean that's ironic. You cheat the guy more and now you
Okay, so that's actually something I put up here. So actually it's
interesting the גמרא Gemara doesn't have the other difference, because one, this
is just ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. אונאה ona has the option of
getting your money back, and this option is all in the hands
of the cheated side, buyer. Well, depends what side is being cheated.
This is either side. Okay. So, so there is a difference. Now
but it's a bigger difference if you think that ביטול מקח bitul
mekach means לעולם, l'olam, right? If it's אונאה, ona, you have a
window of time to ask for your money back, right? You have
a thirty-day return policy if there's a problem. If it's a big
problem, if it comes defective, then you can always get your money
back, right? So the biggest difference would be if this was לעולם
l'olam because it was such an
overcharge, always get my money back. Here I've got a limited amount
of time. If you say this is also limited amount of time,
the differences are smaller. Here you have an option of money back
or ביטול, bitul, here it's only ביטול, bitul, here either side can
ask for ביטול, bitul, here it's only the cheated side. Okay, so
that's what we want to know. Is it possible that this is
limited to עד שיראה? ad sheyer'eh? So מאי, mai, what's the story?
תא שמע ta shma come and hear. חזרו chozru back to the
Rabbi Tarfon's merchants. חזרו לדברי חכמים. chozru l'divrei chachamim. They went back
and they decided they liked the חכמים chachamim better after he said
כל היום. kol hayom. אי אמרת בשלמא ביטול מקח לרבנן בכדי שיראה
לתגר או לקרובו ei amarta b'shma bitul mekach l'rabbanan bichdei sheyer'eh l'tager
o l'krovo ורבי טרפון כל היום, v'rabbi tarfon kol hayom, משום הכי
חזרו. mishum hachi chozru. Ah, so remember here, right? He said here,
whatever he was saying, let's say he was saying אונאה, ona, right?
So אונאה ona is always with a clock, it assumed עד שיראה.
ad sheyer'eh. So now we're saying like this. First, they liked being
on this side. It was עד שיראה ad sheyer'eh and then because,
because they would rather have it be אונאה ona than ביטול מקח
bitul mekach for whatever reason. Okay, we're going to assume אונאה ona
is better even though logically it seems like ביטול מקח bitul mekach
is better. So we understand first they said, oh great, you're giving
us אונאה ona a much bigger range, I'd rather be on that
side than on the ביטול מקח bitul mekach side. Then he says
because they assumed ביטול מקח bitul mekach is עד שיראה. ad sheyer'eh.
Then he says no, no, no, it's not עד שיראה. ad sheyer'eh.
It's כל היום kol hayom
the אונאה. ona. Okay. Then they said, oh, כל היום, kol hayom,
we'd rather have it much more limited, we'd rather be on that
side of the board. So you understand why כל היום kol hayom
makes them want to go to ביטול מקח bitul mekach because if
ביטול מקח bitul mekach has a clock associated with
it, okay. אלא אי אמרת ביטול מקח לרבנן לעולם חוזר, ela ei
amarta bitul mekach l'rabbanan l'olam chozer, but if this was לעולם, l'olam,
okay, so first of all, we don't even know why they wanted
to be on this side of the board, whether it was עד
שיראה ad sheyer'eh or whether it was כל... oh no we do,
excuse me, we know they wanted to be on this side of
the board because they'd much rather it have a clock associated with
it, right, than it be לעולם. l'olam. We get why they liked
this side of the board. What we don't get is why when
he said כל היום kol hayom did they want to go back?
Okay, you know, this is has a clock associated with it even
if it's a כל היום kol hayom clock and this is לעולם.
l'olam? It's the same question we asked before. What would have motivated
them to go back if that was לעולם? l'olam Okay, so right,
so we haven't got that yet, it's just taking from the different
side. אלא אי אמרת ביטול מקח לרבנן לעולם חוזר אמאי חזרו? ela
ei amarta bitul mekach l'rabbanan l'olam chozer amai chozru? בדבי רבי טרפון
ניחא להו. bid'rabbi tarfon nicha l'hu. They should prefer Rabbi Tarfon דקא
מטי ליה אונאה כל היום. d'ka mati lei ona kol hayom. He
calls it אונאה ona but you only have the whole day, it's
a limited time period. ותו לא v'tu lo and after the end
of the day, end of state, end of story, no more option.
ביטול מקח bitul mekach so why would they have preferred to go
back here if this gives them a lot more, I mean if
this, if this gives the buyer a lot more time to get
his, you know whatever, it's much better for the buyer. So that's
a pretty good question. So the גמרא Gemara says ביטול מקח לא
שכיח. bitul mekach lo shchiach. All right, it's not so common that
people are going to charge that much over. I got to tell
you, depending on what the rules are, it's going to become more
common if they can get away with it. But let's bracket that
for a moment. The גמרא Gemara says okay, and you'll throw in
what רש"י Rashi says, which isn't in the גמרא, Gemara, that the
difference between כל היום kol hayom and לעולם l'olam is a relatively
small difference, okay?
So therefore once you said כל היום, kol hayom, the difference of
כל היום kol hayom and לעולם l'olam is not so huge, there's
not going to be a lot more people that are going to
do it. And this anyway is not such a common phenomenon that
it's that much overcharged. So the bigger difference is this difference. This
happens very rarely and the difference is not so great between כל
היום kol hayom and לעולם l'olam. and therefore the bigger difference is
here, that he's going to call a sixth מחילה mchila and they're
going to call a sixth אונאה. ona. All right, just accept it.
Bottom line is, we don't know whether מחילה mchila is automatic and
we don't know whether ביטול מקח bitul mekach is לעולם. l'olam, All
right.
But why would they prefer
חכמים? chachamim?
Because of the אונאה, ona, the exactly one-sixth. He would make it
automatic מחילה mchila and they would and according to them it would
not be automatic מחילה. mchila.
Right, that's why they should prefer Rabbi Tarfon.
Oh. Wait wait wait. He would have it as... oh, you're right.
So why did they go back to the חכמים? Chachamim?
Oh my god. They
right with the Tarfon thing that might as well be... oh, because
I think this side is going back and assuming this. You're right.
This side is going back and assuming what we assumed before, that
the מחילה mechila line is at the same. So they'd rather be
here where the הונאה ona'ah is עד שיראה ad she-yireh rather than
here where the הונאה ona'ah is כל היום. kol ha-yom. Thank you.
Good catch. Okay. I don't know if anybody got the question, but
it was a great point. Okay, we're back to assuming the מחילה
mechila line is there. Anyway, we don't, so we don't know. We
could argue either way. It's all very confusing. Okay. Is it, is
this לעולם, l'olam and is this, and is this לעולם l'olam and
is this automatic? We know הונאה ona'ah is עד שיראה. ad she-yireh.
Okay. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הלכתא... hilchasa... thank you. Let's try to
wrap this up. You may have found it, yeah. הלכות משתות... Hilchos
mishtos... okay, even though there's a debate what רבא Rava means. פחות
משתות, Pachos mishtos, נקנה מקח. nikneh mekach. Less than a sixth, it's
end of sale. And רש"י Rashi and I don't know if I
didn't read all the ראשונים, Rishonim, but רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos
assume that means automatic. Okay. So that's answer number one. Under a
sixth, end of sale, it's automatic. Anything under a sixth is a
tolerable variation in price, and so doesn't really mean that the guy
was aware of it and he was מוחל. mochel. Anything under that,
that's it. You know, that's the tolerable range, and that's not even,
that happens automatically. Good. That solves that. Okay, now, we're going to
ignore Rabbi Tarfon now. Okay, we're just going to look at this
question. Okay. That's automatic. יתר על שתות, ביטול מקח. Yeter al shtut
bitul mekach,
All right, that we knew. What we don't know is whether it's
לעולם l'olam, or not. Okay. We'll find out. Now, well,
that's a good question. You know, you would think that if it's
so grossly overcharged and the phrase ביטול מקח bitul mekach. means that
it just automatically, you know... but based on the language of the
גמרא, Gemara, שניהם חוזרין, shneichem chozrin,
and even תוספות Tosfos sometimes even says that this actually addresses a
little bit of the irony problem. The irony is, I'm going to
overcharge you more, and that's going to give me the right to
be מבטל. mevatel. Right, that's pretty ironic. So תוספות Tosfos actually suggests,
no, I don't have the right to initiate the ביטול bitul if
I overcharged you more, if I, you know... what happens is you
come to me, you were way overcharged, and you say like give
me my money back. And I'm going to say no, I'm not
going to give you your money back, I'll cancel the sale if
you want me to, you know... but anyway, but I only have
the right to do it in response to you, I don't have
the right to do it unilaterally. Anyway, but the point is, so
that's not clear. It's ironic that once you get higher, right, the
other, the seller, the one who cheated, did the cheating, right, has
more, you know, seems to have more options. But Michael also asked
a very important question, which is, is it just automatic, the sale
is completely a false sale and it's בטל, batel, or does it
have to be one of the... at least one side is opting
to do ביטול מקח? bitul mekach Clearly when the גמרא Gemara thought
that it was עד שיראה, ad she-yireh, it needed a side to
initiate the ביטול מקח. bitul mekach? It was not automatic. When we
say it's לעולם, l'olam it's more of an open issue, but the
language very much suggests that it's not automatic. לעולם l'olam means you
have, you always have the option of ביטול מקח, bitul mekach. but
it doesn't happen automatically. So this is ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, this
is מחילה, mechila, okay, but this, yes, this is basically saying nothing
happened here. That's a tolerable price variation. This is saying no, no,
no, there was a gross overcharging and either side has the right
to demand a ביטול מקח. bitul mekach, Okay, but we have not
yet decided the לעולם le'olam issue. Yes.
You wouldn't want it to be automatic without either party initiating because
then you're having all these people walking around with things they think
they own, and they don't. Right.
That's a good point. That's a very good point, just as a
policy point. Yeah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
שתות, shtos, exactly at a sixth... so, it's bizarre that the whole
idea of הונאה ona'ah that we talk about is this exact pinpoint
exact price thing. At least according to שמואל Shmuel it's a little
bit of a range. Okay, right, remember שמואל Shmuel has like a
range within the sixth. שתות, קנה ומחזיר אונאה. Shtut kana u-machzir ona'ah.
Okay. The... it now works but you have to give the overcharge
back.
The whole thing. Just get that back. One minute.
Now, have to pause for a moment. That sounds different than what
we said up until now. Until we said now, we said if
it's a sixth and it's הונאה, ona'ah, what do we say, what
do we say the consequence of it being הונאה ona'ah was? Two
options. You have two options. We said you could either get your
overcharge back or ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. This just
says קנה ומחזיר אונאה, koneh u-machazir ona'ah. doesn't say that you could
opt for ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. So רש"י Rashi actually says that
this rejects what we were saying before and we're about to quote
a ברייתא Baraisa where רבי נתן... Rabbi Nason... this is רבי נתן's
Rabbi Nason position. רבי נתן's Rabbi Nason position is you can just
get your overcharge, you cannot opt for ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. תוספות
Tosfos disagrees. תוספות Tosfos says that the גמרא Gemara is... this is...
רבא Rava isn't getting into that. רבא Rava would never פוסק paskin
like רבי נתן Rabbi Nason against the חכמים. Chachamim. All the evidence
is the חכמים. Chachamim. So רבא Rava does not mean דוקא davka
you can't... your money back, he means, he still means you have
a choice. Okay? What? The unique aspect.
The unique
aspect is you can get your money back. The ביטול מקח, bitul
mekach. yes, that applies as well. Okay, so there's an important question
whether we are changing your options in terms of אונאה, ona'ah, we'll
get back to that, but let's now finish the thought here. Okay,
just
now, where were we? וזה בזה כדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו. Ve-zeh
va-zeh be-khdei she-yera’eh le-tagar o li-krovo. Now וזה בזה ve-zeh va-zeh is
what? Which of like which of them? So again רש״י Rashi says
it's not explicit, but רש״י Rashi says וזה בזה ve-zeh va-zeh is
a ביטול מקח bitul mekach, and אונאה. ona'ah. Okay, so this is
a clock. After you wait עד כדי שיראה, ad k'dei she-yera'eh, you've
lost your option of getting your money back or ביטול מקח. bitul
mekach Even if it's grossly overcharged. Okay, after and that just is
also your policy question, Jenna. Even if it's grossly overcharged, you have
a right until a certain type of a point, you know, there's
a certain window that you can demand a reversal, which clearly shows
that it's not automatic. That one side has to basically opt to
do ביטול מקח bitul mekach. and you have a window of time.
You have עד כדי שיראה. ad k'dei she-yera'eh. So in terms of
our question before, okay, this seems to be that this is automatic.
Okay, it's not explicit in Rava's statement but this is the way
רש״י Rashi reads it, and these, which means that's just a tolerable
range variation, and these, you've been cheated, you're given a period of
time to identify that you've been cheated and to and to opt
to get for redress. After that time has passed, you have lost
your options, which is funny. You would think ביטול מקח bitul mekach
would be לעולם le'olam, if you've really been cheated that much, but
I certainly hear Jenna's point which is, you know, you can't deal
with, you can't go through life knowing that, you know, 10 years
later somebody can go ahead and say, you know, whatever. Now of
course there's some bit, there are periods between עד כדי שיראה ad
k'dei she-yera'eh and לעולם, le'olam. but yes, that's not being considered.
And this is as long as somebody, the buyer keeps the goods
according to whatever period you said that the seller can't come and
say.
Right, but anyway, but you do understand policy reasons why we don't
want to give these options, you know, for too long.
And maybe opposite though, like if something breaks you can bring it
back.
Right. I understand.
And really in context
I get it, I get it. Okay. So anyway, so this is
basically the way we seem to be concluding. All right. According now,
well, right, according to רש״י, Rashi, that's how he reads that. And
the difference, now what is the difference between ביטול מקח bitul mekach
and אונאה? ona'ah? So ביטול מקח bitul mekach is ביטול מקח, bitul
mekach אונאה ona'ah is you can get your overcharge back. Okay, now
how about can by אונאה ona'ah you also opt for ביטול מקח?
bitul mekach, Okay. Oh, also this is either side can opt for
it, and
אונאה ona'ah it is only the cheated side can opt for it.
How do we know that?
Because the גמרא Gemara said it a minute ago. The גמרא Gemara
said ביטול מקח וזה בזה bitul mekach ve-zeh va-zeh when it was
working with the whole רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and לעולם. le'olam, שניהם
חוזרים עד כדי שיראה. shneichem chozrim ad k'dei she-yera'eh. Right, I'm just
trying to pull things together. And the one thing that's not clear
is when רבא Rava says you get your overcharge, is רבא Rava
rejecting what we've been saying until now which is do you also
have an option of ביטול מקח? bitul mekach? Okay, רש״י Rashi says
רבא Rava is rejecting it, תוספות Tosfos says it's not, and that
is going to be the debate here of רבי Rebbi and רבי
נתן. Rabbi Natan. Does תוספות Tosfos agree that ביטול מקח bitul mekach?
is also עד כדי
שיראה?
ad k'dei
she-yera'eh?
Yes, he reads it that way. The גמרא Gemara says עד וזה
בזה. ad ve-zeh va-zeh. Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara,
now the only difference between רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos what you're
saying is that ביטול מקח bitul mekach and אונאה ona'ah is this.
Right. Exactly. Yep. Okay. So now let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תני כוותיה דרבא, Tani kavatei de-Rava, we taught like
רבא. Rava. אונאה פחות משתות נקנה מקח, Ona'ah pachot mi-shtut nikna mekach,
less than a שתות shtos, it's sale is final. יתר על שתות
Yoser al shtos, ביטול מקח, bitul mekach more it's
בטל, batel,
you know. שתות shtut קנה ומחזיר אונאה. koneh u-machazir ona'ah, Exactly רבא's
Rava language, right? דברי רבי נתן. Divrei Rabbi Natan. Now that's why
רש״י Rashi says רבא's Rava פסקן pasken like רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan.
There's only one thing, get the overage back. Okay, it is there's
no other choice by the אונאה. ona'ah. רבי יהודה הנשיא אומר לא
יד מוכר על העליונה. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi omer lo yad mocher al
ha-elyona. If it is the מוכר mocher who is cheated, it's funny
that רבי Rebbi is giving the example that the מוכר mocher is
cheated, but the basic point is whichever side is cheated, that side
has the
options. רצה אומר לו תן לי מקחי. Ratza omer lo ten li
mikchi. You can either say give me my the object I sold
back if the מוכר mocher was cheated and underpaid. או תן לי
מה שאוניתני, O ten li mah she-onitani, or give me back or
pay me the extra amount that you should have been paying me,
the underage that you didn't pay me. וזה בזה כדי שיראה לתגר
או לקרובו. Ve-zeh va-zeh be-khdei she-yera'eh le-tagar o li-krovo. Okay, so there
it is. So this is the debate whether you have this choice
of ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, that is the debate of רבי Rebbi
and רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. All right. So now good, we've finally
come to some conclusion. Okay, it was not
exactly clear whether this was going to be automatic or whether this
was going to be לעולם, le'olam but at least the way רש״י
Rashi and תוספות Tosfos understand the conclusion, this is automatic and this
is עד כדי שיראה.
ad k'dei she-yera'eh. דאקייט. Da-keit.
Wait, let's Right, meaning that's interesting like why, how does רבא Rava
get to that פסק הלכה? psak halacha? Was he basing it on
the ברייתא? Baraita? Like the גמרא Gemara couldn't prove it either way,
so how, where was he coming? That's always a question. The גמרא
Gemara asks a question, doesn't have any textual evidence and then someone
just פוסק, paskens, right? But yeah, but we're not rejecting the גמרא
Gemara from before, it's just that it was inconclusive. Yeah.
It strikes me, your example of Land's End is a really good
example. In other words, it's an example of the application of לעולם
incentivizes a huge customer population.
Right, they don't lose. The merchant doesn't lose anything.
So it's actually like a really good example. I don't know how
they could have possibly been profitable.
But they did. And obviously not everybody believes in it because that's
why Land's End is distinctive in terms of that way. Yeah.
And it's an agrarian society, right? What, it's that
they make a distinction between produce and that affects the timeline because
they
don't care here with... Oh no, that's a good point, but they
do not make that. We will see some distinctions coming up a
little bit, but about the types of products or whatever, but basically
the short answer is no. But let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes. Okay, we're going to move on. Okay חברא, chevra, let's see
because now it gets easy and let's make, we're going to make
a push. Okay. עד מתי מותר להחזיר? Ad masai mutar lehachzir? Until
when can you get the money back? Okay, עד שיעיר ad sheya'ir
and again, רבן, Rabban, who was it? רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
his merchants there and said you have a whole day. רבי טרפון,
Rabbi Tarfon, excuse me. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, now here's
going to blow your mind. לא שנו אלא לוקח. Lo shanu ela
loke'ach. It's only the buyer who has a time limit to get
his money
back. אבל מוכר, Aval mocher, his overcharge, אבל מוכר לעולם חוזר. aval
mocher le'olam chozer. He can, now of course you think but come
on, the seller should know his business better, right? Of anybody, the
seller shouldn't even be able to say he was cheated. Now, not
only does the seller, can the seller say he was cheated and
he was underpaid, but he can forever ask to get either the
difference back or presumably ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. Why? What's the reason?
So the גמרא Gemara says, let's take a look. נימא מסייע ליה,
Neima misayei lei, let's try to prove it. חזרו לדברי חכמים. Chazru
ledivrei chachamim.
רבי טרפון's, Rabbi Tarfon the merchants who went back. So now we're
not going to get into the whole complicated thing we did before,
we're just going to say a simple point, which is that any
policy, if it's equal on both sides, מוכר mocher and לוקח, loke'ach,
any policy equally benefits both sides or equally hurts both sides. But
if you say like you're saying, that the מוכר mocher always has
a longer period of time,
then the מוכר mocher sort of would like a policy that expands
the definition of
אונאה ona'ah because
wait, wait, yes, because that benefits them, okay? So the גמרא Gemara
says like because they'll always have more time and the other side
will always have a more limited time. אי אמרת בשלמא מוכר לעולם
חוזר, I amarta beshalma mocher le'olam chozer, if the מוכר mocher
has all the amount of time to be חוזר, chozer, משום הכי
חזרו. mishum hachi chazru. They'd rather be on the חכמים chachamim side
of the equation, because the חכמים chachamim side gives the purchaser shorter
period of time, gives the purchaser עד שיעיר ad sheya'ir and they
retain forever. So you'd much rather have a policy that says עד
שיעיר ad sheya'ir if it only applies to the purchaser, if it
only applies to the buyer, okay, right? So they'd prefer the shorter
period of time. אלא אי אמרת מוכר נמי כלוקח דמי, Ela i
amarta mocher nami keloke'ach dami, but if the period of time equally
impacts, is equally true for the buyer or the seller depending on
which side is cheated, so מאי נפקא להו מיניה? mai nafka lehu
minei? What do they care whether the period of time is כל
היום kol hayom or the period of time is עד שיעיר, ad
sheya'ir, whether it's bigger or smaller? It equally impacts the buyer as
it does
the seller. כי היכי דעבדו ליה רבנן תקנתא ללוקח הכי נמי עבדו
רבנן תקנתא למוכר. Ki heichi de'avdu lei rabanan takanta leloke'ach hachi nami
avdu rabanan takanta lemocher. The same way the רבנן's rabanan position
limits the buyer's options or whatever, it also limits the seller's options.
So any period of time, why would you prefer a shorter period
of time? You prefer a shorter period of time if you're the
seller because it limits the buyer, but it also limits you if
you're the side that's cheated, okay?
So you're talking about how wide the אונאה ona'ah window is?
How much time, that's the פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah focused
on the fact that when רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said I'm giving
people a whole day, they said, ah, you're giving a whole day,
we'd rather be with the רבנן rabanan only give people a few
hours. But you also only have a few hours if you're the
cheated side, so why do you care? What difference does it make?
רש"י's Rashi explanation is...
so the גמרא Gemara says, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
גמרא Gemara says תגרי לוד לא שכיח דטעו. tagrei lod lo shachiach
detu. No,
come on, give me a break. Those merchants know what they're doing.
If you don't know what you're meaning, bottom line is, who's going
to be cheated nine times out of ten? The buyer, not the
seller. Okay, so therefore even if it's true that in the rare
case that I the seller am cheated, this shorter period of time
hurts me, I'd rather... I'd rather have a shorter period of time
to have your options because nine times out of ten, it's the
buyer who's being cheated and it hurts the buyer more than it
hurts me. So you don't need it to be that I have
forever. We could all be limited by the amount of time and
I still stand to gain by this policy, okay, by a limited
period of time. Okay, so we don't know. Now, we haven't explained
why the buyer will have more time to reverse than the seller,
but we're going to clarify it. So let's take a look.
אושפיזכני דרמי בר חמא, Uspizchei de-Rami bar Chama, so Rami
bar Chama's
innkeeper, I always get confused when it means
the innkeeper or the host. I think it means the host here.
How's it translated? Landlord, right. Yeah, it's the innkeeper, okay, זבין חמרא,
zavin chamra,
he sold wine. וטעה, veta, and now so
he's the seller and he made a mistake, he undersold it. אשכחיה
דהוה יתיב, azkheih de-hava yativ,
so Rami bar Chama found that he was sitting in anguish. אמר
ליה אמאי עציבת, amlei amai ativat, why are you so sad? אמר
ליה זביני חמרי וטעאי, amlei zavin chamri veta'ai, because I sold wine
and I made a mistake, I grossly undersold it for its value.
אמר ליה amlei, אמאי עציבת, why are you so sad?
I skipped a line. אמר ליה Amar Lei, זיל הדר בך, go,
okay, so go reverse it, you still have time. אמר ליה לא
השתא יהא לי יותר מכדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו, amlei lo hashta
yehei li yoter mikdei she-yeira'eh le-tagar o le-kerovo, I lost my option,
I waited more than the three
hours, okay. So שדריה לקמיה דרב נחמן, shadrei lekamei de-Rav Nachman, he
said go talk to Rav Nachman, maybe he can help you out,
okay. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so Rav Nachman said to him, בכדי
שיראה ללוקח, be-khedei she-yeira'eh la-lokeach, so that's the same thing Rav Nachman
said right before we came to the new page, אבל מוכר לעולם
חוזר. aval mocher le-olam chozer. Oh, not a problem, you're a seller.
Seller, you have the option to be חוזר chozer even after a
long period of time. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, now finally we're
saying what's the logic behind this? לוקח מקחו בידו, lokeach mikcho biyado,
because the לוקח lokeach has what he bought in his hand. כל
היכא דאזיל מחוי ליה, kol heicha de-azil machvei leh, so anywhere he
goes, he says look what I bought, I got this great new
Armani suit for only a hundred dollars. ואמרי ליה אטעו לא אטעו,
ve'amrei leh it'u lo it'u, buddy, that was a knockoff, you got
cheated or not. So he can show it to people and they'll
tell him. So he's got a limited amount of time because he
will soon find out if he was cheated or not. מוכר דלא
נקיט מקחו בידיה, mocher delo nakit mikcho biyadei, now a seller who
is not holding onto the object. He's like, I sold wine and
now I think I sold him stuff that was like, wine has
a wide variation, ten dollars a bottle or two hundred dollars a
bottle. So I think I sold him stuff grossly underpriced. Well, how
do you know? You're not holding onto the wine that you can
now get a good assessment of the price, okay. מוכר דלא נקיט
מקחו בידיה, mocher delo nakit mikcho biyadei, he's not holding onto the
object that
he sold, עד דמי רמי ליה זבינתא כזבינתא, ad mi-rami leh zvinta
k'zvinta, until he has an opportunity to find an object like the
one that he sold, וידע אטעו ולא אטעו, veyada it'u velo it'u,
and then and only then will he know if he made a
mistake. And we don't know how long that will take. When am
I going to find wine of the similar quality that I'll be
able to get somebody to assess it and determine whether I undersold
it or not? So we give him forever. So it's quite ironic,
right? I think our intuition would have been maybe a מוכר mocher
should have no options, he should know his business, or if anything
much fewer options to demand a refund, and here we're telling him,
no you actually have much more time because you won't always know
after the fact, be easy to assess whether you were cheated or
not.
I've got a question here, your
theme for, but you said that oh it's a knockoff Armani, that's
different than
the, fine,
okay, that might be more of a מקח טעות, mekach ta'us, that's
true. Moving on. ההוא גברא דהוה
נקיט ורשכי, hu gavra de-havi nakit varsakhei, ורשכי, varsakhei, Rashi, if you
look at Rashi, Rashi says ורשכי, varsakhei, Rashi says four lines from
the top, כשורי משי, keshurei meshi, משי meshi is like
silk, דקורין בינדל.
shekorin
bindle.
Okay, so that's I think Rashi, בינדל, bindle, like little bracelets, right?
Is that what a בינדל bindle is? Not a Yiddish word? Nobody
knows? Okay, anyway. לזבוני, le-zavuni, anyway, he was selling these bracelets or
whatever he was selling. קרי שיתא, kari shisha, he was saying six
dollars, six dollars. ושוי חמשה, veshavei chamsha, it was only worth five.
He was announcing for six. We're going to assume like שמאול Shmuel
by the way, that that's אונאה, ona'ah, it's not ביטול מקח, bitul
mekach, right? Remember the six is what he's paying, it's not worth
it, whatever, if people remember שמאול. Shmuel. Anyway, it was worth five
and he was announcing
six. ואילו יהבי ליה חמשה ופלגא הוה שקיל, ve'ilu yava leh chamsha
palga havi shakil, but if somebody would come and haggle and basically
say I'll tell you what I'll give you five and a half,
he would have accepted that too. אתא ההוא גברא ואמר, ata hu
gavra ve'amar, somebody came and he said to himself, אי יהיבנא ליה
חמשה ופלגא, ee yahivna leh chamsha palga, if I offer him five
and a half, הוי מחילה, havi mechila, then I'm in this zone
and the sale will be final and I won't be able to
get my half dollar back. So you know what I'm going to
do? I'm going to, אייתי ואשקול שיתא, aytei ve-eshkol shita, I'll actually
intentionally pay him more and give him six and then it'll be
אונאה. ona'ah. ...and then I'll be entitled for my whole dollar back,
okay? The entire overcharge. ואתייה לדינא, V'ateiyeh LeDina, and then I'll come
and I'll bring him to דין, Din, okay? So this also shows
you the irony. This some of this makes such, you know, little
sense. You more overcharge, that gives you as the seller more options.
Okay, you're the buyer, you're more cheated. I mean in some way
it makes sense if you don't know what you're doing. Once you're
cheated more, then you're entitled to get your full overage within this
it's tolerable. But if you know what you're doing, you'll want yourself
to be cheated more after and then after you pay the six
because he's not going to sell it for five. You can either
buy it for five and a half or for six. So if
you sell for five and a half, end of story. But if
you sell it for six and then bring him to a בית
דין, Beis Din, then you'll get your one back and you'll have
managed to buy it for five. Okay?
Two people who are going to take advantage and not people who
are being taken advantage of.
Exactly, exactly. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
yeah, and then sue. Okay. And then with all those lawyers,
right, exactly, you have to pay lawyer fees. Okay, אתו לקמיה דרבא,
Atu L'Kamei D'Rava, came to Rava. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, לא שנו.
Lo Shanu. Now
Rava, in principle you're right. If you know what you're doing and
you're the buyer and you actually get it into this zone, you'll
be able to get your full overage back. You're better to be
in this zone and know what you're doing than to be in
this zone. But there's another reason this won't work in this case.
אמר amar ליה, לא שנו אלא בלוקח מן התגר. Lo Shanu Ella
B'Lokei'ach Min HaTagar. That's only if you buy from a merchant. אבל
בלוקח מבעל הבית אין לו עליו אונאה. Aval B'Lokei'ach MiBaal HaBayis Ein
Lo Alav Ona'ah. Here's another exception which is when you buy from
a homeowner who is basically selling personal goods, privately and selling personal
goods, then we say that those have like, you know, sentimental value
and those cannot just be, you know, and they are entitled to
charge what they will for them. You know, it's up to you
to decide if you want to pay it. Okay, but you'll never
ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach. Never ביטול מקח, Bitul Mekach, never אונאה. Ona'ah.
It seems to be right. Maybe he's only saying exactly a sixth,
but basically the way רש"י Rashi seems to read it is like
no, you have to know, these are my own personal goods and
I'm charging you what I, you know, I'm not telling you that
this is the market price for this. I'm not implicitly making that
claim. Okay, I'm selling you my own personal items and this is
what I need.
It basically is what it is?
Like wine? Well, yeah, it might be. Yes, yes, yes. It basically
is when you're dealing with personal items. Okay? So by the way
though, another law that benefits sellers. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
what?
It's only worth five, right in the text, right?
What? It said, it said six. Yeah, that's what it's market value
is. But since I am a homeowner and I am selling my
personal items, I don't care what its market value is. All right?
You know? Okay. ההוא גברא דהוה נקיט כיפי לזבוני, Hahu Gavra D'Hava
Nakit Kifi L'Zivuni, somebody who was heard to have selling rings, like
nose rings or something. Okay. קרי שיתין, Kari Shitin, he sold them,
he was selling them, he was announcing that they were going for
sixty. ושוו חמשין, V'Shavei Chamshin, and but they were really only worth
fifty. אי הוה יהבי ליה חמשין וחמשה, Ei Hava Yahavi Lei Chamshin
V'Chamshat, it's exact same thing that we said before except times ten.
But if they would have given him fifty-five, הוה שקיל, Hava Shakil,
he would have
accepted. אתו גברא ואמר, Atu Gavra V'Amar, somebody came and said look,
אי יהיבנא ליה חמשין וחמשה, Ei Yahivna Lei Chamshin V'Chamshat, if I
give him fifty-five, הויא מחילה, Havi Mechilah, then that'll be the end
of it. I won't get my five back. So
אתן ליה שיתין, Eten Lei Shitin, I'll give him sixty, ואתייה לדינא,
V'ateiyeh LeDina, and then I'll go ahead and bring him to court
and I'll get my whole ten back and I'll manage to have
bought it for fifty. אתו לקמיה דרב חסדא, Atu L'Kamei D'Rav Chisda,
came to Rav
Chisda. אמר ליה, לא שנו אלא בלוקח מן התגר. Lo Shanu Ella
B'Lokei'ach Min HaTagar. It's only when you buy from a merchant do
these rules apply. אבל לוקח מבעל הבית אין לו עליו אונאה. Aval
Lokei'ach MiBaal HaBayis Ein Lo Alav Ona'ah. But when it's from a
בעל הבית, Baal HaBayis, you do not have this right. Now again,
does that mean even ביטול מקח, Bitul Mekach, grossly overcharged, we're only
dealing with a sixth? Not clear. But anyway, when somebody is selling
their personal effects then you have to understand that the price won't
exactly be the same as the market price.
אמר ליה רב דימי משום דהוה מעשה אחר
Amar Lei Rav Dimi Mishum
D'Hava Ma'aseh Achar because it was a different story, I mean it's
a parallel story but it was a different story. It was with
different things being sold, it was different amounts, one was רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, the other was who, was רבא. Rava. Okay. What? Personal
items, you'd say? Well, we haven't gotten to that. We're going to
say that more explicitly now. That hasn't been said explicitly. I've been
adding that point. אמר ליה רב דימי Amar Lei Rav Dimi so
Rav Dimi said ישר. Yasher. Yeah, יישר כחך, Yasher Koachacha, that's right,
that's a good פסק. Psak. וכן אמר רבי אלעזר V'chein Amar Rabi
Elazar ישר. Yasher. ורמינן תנן, Ur'minan Tnan, כשם שאונאה להדיוט כך אונאה
לתגר. Kesheim She'Ona'ah L'Hedyot Kach Ona'ah L'Tagar.
One minute, we have a משנה Mishna coming up that says the
same rules that apply to a merchant apply to a layperson. So
presumably a layperson means a homeowner, right? So isn't that saying that
it's the same rules and you're saying it's different rules? So the
גמרא Gemara says no. מאי הדיוט, Mai Hedyot, who's a הדיוט? Hedyot?
לאו בעל הבית? Lav Baal HaBayis? Doesn't that mean a homeowner selling
their personal effects? אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, בצדרייתא. B'Tzadrayta. We're
talking about which is basically canvas bags and this is my point
before about personal effects. Yes, we are talking about a homeowner, but
a homeowner selling things like canvas bags, things that are not, you
know, not something that you have any like personal attachment to. So
those types of things even if a homeowner sells, if you go
ahead and you bought apples and you bought too many apples and
then you're going to sell your apples to your next-door neighbor, right?
Yes, it has the same rules of אונאה. Ona'ah. אבל מאני תשמישתיה,
Aval Manei Tashmishtei, but
personal, you know, effects, like personal things that you use. use, okay,
that are your own, so דייקרי ליה, d'yakrei lei, that those are
dear to him, לא מזבין להו אלא בדמי יתירה. lo mzabin lehu
ela bidmei yeitirei. You won't sell it except you're going to actually
ask for more money. You want to buy my own, you know,
whatever it is, you know, my set of dishes. I don't care
that used dishes on eBay go for, you know, a dollar a
place setting. You know, these are the ones I got from my
grandmother, and you know, I really don't care what you can get
them for on eBay.
Okay, yes. Rashi says it specifically means like canvas bags. Okay, but
it represents Rashi.
What? בדי קנבוס? B'dei kannabus? Cannabis?
Cannabis? Okay, right, okay. Okay. So, well, cannabis, cannabis, you know
that that's cannabis. Yes. Okay, that's what you were saying. Yeah, yeah,
okay.
Hemp. Hemp. Right?
Hemp bag. What do we classify as cannabis overcharging? We don't like...
I've heard...
What? About what? About in this case? I don't know. I don't
know. I don't know. Shh! Next משנה, mishnah, people. Behave. Okay. אחד
הלוקח ואחד המוכר יש
בהם אונאה. Echad halokeach v'echad hamocher yesh bahem ona'ah. So now we
have the משנה mishnah that should have maybe been the first משנה,
mishnah, whether the seller or the buyer, it applies whether overcharge or
undercharge. כשם שאונאה להדיוט כך אונאה לתגר, K'shem she'ona'ah l'hedyot kach ona'ah
l'tagar, like we said before, it doesn't matter whether you're a homeowner
or a merchant. And presumably doesn't matter as a buyer or as
a seller, right? Where we could understand one minute, this guy is
a seller and it's his business, like don't tell me he has
a right to ask, he can say he was cheated. No, it
doesn't matter. Homeowner, seller, you know, it's all the same rules.
Okay. רבי יהודה אומר אין אונאה לתגר. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein ona'ah
l'tagar. No, no, no. A merchant cannot claim אונאה, ona'ah, presumably... now
we would say it means that, like, you know, you should know
your business and it's your own fault. The גמרא Gemara is going
to say a variation of that, but that certainly makes a lot
of sense. מי שהוטעה ידו על העליונה. Mi she'huta yado al ha'elyona.
The person who was cheated has the options. If it's exactly the
אונאה ona'ah we're talking about now about the exact אונאה ona'ah amount.
רצה אומר לו תן לי מעותי או תן לי מה שאוניתני. Ratzah
omer lo ten li me'otai o ten li mah she'onitani. If he
was... if the buyer was the cheated side, which is usually, he
can say give me the over... give me back all my money,
reverse the sale, or give me back my overage. Okay. מנא הני
מילי. mana hanei milei. Finally, where do we know that there's a
prohibition of אונאה? ona'ah? דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, our Rabbis taught.
וכי תמכרו ממכר
לעמיתך
אל תונו או קנה מיד עמיתך,
V'chi
timkeru mimkar
la'amitecha
al tonu o kano miyad amitecha, right. וכי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך אל
תונו, V'chi timkeru mimkar la'amitecha al tonu, אין לי אלא שנתאנה לוקח.
ein li ela shenit'ana lokeach.
If you sell something don't cheat, don't overcharge.
That's only if the buyer is cheated. נתאנה מוכר מנין, Nit'ana mocher
minayin, how do you know if the seller is cheated? תלמוד לומר
או קנה, Talmud lomar o kano, or when you're buying, don't cheat.
So even as a buyer you're not allowed to cheat the seller.
איצטריך למכתב לוקח ואיצטריך למכתב מוכר. Itztrich lemichtav lokeach v'itztrich lemichtav mocher.
You had to tell me both sides are restricted. דאי כתב רחמנא
מוכר, De'i katav rachmana mocher, if it just said where the seller
was restricted, משום דקים ליה בזבינתיה. mishum d'kaim lei b'zvinthei. Thank you
very much. He knows what he's doing. He knows his business. אבל
לוקח, Aval lokeach, so therefore he cannot cheat the buyer. אבל לוקח
דלא קים ליה בזבינתיה, Aval lokeach d'lo kaim lei b'zvinthei, the buyer
is not such a businessman, so אימא לא אזהר רחמנא בלא תונו.
eima lo azhar rachmana belo tonu. You know,
maybe he is not prohibited to not, you know, not cheat the
buyer because A, he does not... he's not so much in the
business and he's not so much taking advantage. I mean, again, we
assume that the people that are buying are not like businessmen who
are doing buying and selling, you know, they're homeowners that are doing
buying. So he's not so much in a position to take advantage
and the way to sort of flip it is also, and the
seller, it's a little to his own blame if he's not, you
know, if he's not paying attention to what's going on. So I
might think that from the buyer side you're not prohibited. Okay. ואי
כתב רחמנא לוקח, V'i katav rachmana lokeach, if it just said that
the buyer can't cheat the seller, משום
דקקני, mishum d'kakani, because at least he is getting the better of
the deal. This is very interesting. This really reflects, you know, a
non-commercial society. Like if we said who's doing better off, the sellers
or the buyers? It's of course the sellers. That's what the business
is, right? You're in the process... you're in the business of selling
books, of selling this, of selling whatever. You're the one making the
money. But the גמרא Gemara sort of sees it more, you know,
let's... commercial... it's funny to say this because it's clear from the
גמרא Gemara that commerce was a big thing. So I really don't
fully understand that, but I guess before it had really exploded, the
world of commerce, okay, the גמרא Gemara actually said it's better to
actually have hold on to objects than just get the money for
them. Because you know, once you have money, money runs through your
fingers. You know, you don't hold on to it. Like objects is
seen as something that's more stays with you and is permanent or
so on. That's... I can't fully explain it, that's the גמרא's Gemara
mentality. Okay. I mean certainly that would be true in an agricultural
society. I just don't get it if the גמרא Gemara seems to
be going already with a commercial one. Okay. ואי כתב רחמנא לוקח,
V'i katav rachmana lokeach, if it just said that the buyer can't
cheat, משום דקקני, mishum d'kakani, he's getting something really worthwhile out of
it. So he's in a privileged position. דאמרי אינשי, D'amrei inshi, זבנת
קניתא. zavnes kanisa. If you bought something then you actually have something
now to hold on to. Okay, so he's in a privileged position.
He shouldn't cheat the seller. אבל מוכר דאבודי קא מוביד, Aval mocher
d'avudei ka movid, the seller is losing something of value. He's losing
a real concrete object. דאמרי אינשי, D'amrei inshi, זבנית אובדית. zavnit ovdit.
You sold something, the money is going away. Like you know, money
burns a hole in your pocket. So you sold something, the cash
is going to whatever. So you are the losing side when you
sell. So the seller who is seen to be
in a
disadvantage No, a better position. They they have they could pay the
like
five US dollars for this investment that's going to feed them for
a month, but the bargaining, you know, rules say that they could
get them down to one dollar.
It's like, yeah, it's a good point. I mean, clearly you're right,
you have to understand the dynamics of the society, you're right. So
clearly reflecting something like that. רבי יהודה אומר אינו אלא תגר. Rebbi
Yehuda omer eino ela tager. משום שהוא תגר אין לו אונאה? mishum
shehu tager ein lo ona'ah?
Just because he's a merchant, not sellers. Sellers have אונאה. ona'ah. If
you're a homeowner and you're a seller, there is אונאה. ona'ah. But
if you're a merchant, then it's not. So now what does that
mean? Does that mean as a merchant I can cheat and I
can overcharge?
So you know, no. It's going to mean that if I'm a
merchant and I underpay. Okay? So משום שהוא תגר אין לו אונאה
אמר רב נחמן אמר רב בתגר ספסר שנו. mishum shehu tager ein
lo ona'ah amar Rav Nachman amar Rav betager safsar shanu. We're talking
about a person that's not just סתם stam a merchant, but he
actually is a, like a, what's it called, like a retailer. Okay,
he's a, there's a better word for that anyway. What? Wholesaler? A
wholesaler? Anyway, somebody who like quickly buys and then turns it over.
Okay, is that a wholesaler? Okay anyway, because that person obviously knows
exactly the prices. It's like arbitrage, right? You know, whatever it is,
like, you know, you're immediately pricing something and selling it for a
profit. So you totally know your business. There is no chance here.
Right, I guess the point is, like if I have a fruit
stand, a vegetable stand, and I'm the farmer, I might not, I
might be the seller but not know my business, you know, so
well of the exact right best price to ask. But if I
am buying from ראובן Reuven and selling to שמעון, Shimon, I know
exactly what price I paid and what price I have to charge
and I totally know my business. So in that type of a
case where I'm buying and selling and the price is very clear
what my profit is and what the price I paid was, so
if I'm going to undercharge I'm to blame for myself. There's nobody
to, I don't know, okay, there's nobody to blame but me. Well,
let's take a look. Okay, it says like this. בתגר ספסר שנו.
betager safsar shanu. מאי טעמא מידע ידע כמה זבין וכמה שווי. mai
ta'ama meida yada kama zavin vekama shavei.
You know exactly how much you paid for it. וחולי הכי וגבי?
vechulei hachi vegabei? And if you undercharge, you cannot say you were
cheated. If you undercharge, you're just being מוחל. mochel. So why would
you be מוחל? mochel? I mean, how could you be so stupid?
So the גמרא Gemara says והאי דזבין הכי משום דאיצטריכו ליה זוזי
אחריני. vehai dezavin hachi mishum de'itztarichu lei zuzei acharinei. You needed liquid
cash, so you decided to sell it at a loss. והשתא מיהא
קיהדר ביה. vehashtah miha ka-hadar bei. And now after you sold it
at a loss and you got the cash that you wanted or
whatever, now you're trying to go back and get your money back.
Okay, but if you totally know your business and for something, for
a business reason, you sold it at a low price in order
to move it because you needed cash, you can't say מקח טעות.
mekach ta'ut. That makes a lot of sense. Okay רב אשי אמר.
Rav Ashi amar.
מאי אין לתגר אונאה? mai ein letager ona'ah? What does it mean
תגר tager doesn't have אונאה? ona'ah? אינו בתורת אונאה. einu betorat ona'ah.
It means the opposite. It means that the normal rules don't apply,
the normal divisions don't apply. שאפילו פחות מכדי אונאה חוזר. she'afillu pachot
mikdei ona'ah chozer. That even if there's a less, you know, less
than this amount...
אין
מחילה.
ein
mechila.
Right away. He's the buyer now, one minute. אם נתאנה? im nit-ana?
Oh no, so this is very bizarre, right? Again, it's the exact
opposite of what we would say. If I went ahead and I,
you know, sold something for like even one dollar less,
I'm the seller, so even one dollar less than the market rate
I'm allowed to ask for the difference. We don't give the buyer
a pass. Why not? I mean, again, I should know my business
and so on. So רש״י Rashi says yeah, but because this is
my פרנסה, parnassah, I am, you know, I am more entitled to
get my sort of the full value of it, okay. So even
if I, even if the undercharge was just a little bit, I'm
entitled to get it paid back where normally you wouldn't. And again,
the explanation is I'm not just a normal homeowner who's buying and
selling, this is my business, and if it's my business, like, you
know, I'm entitled to get the full amount.
If not, it's an opposite interpretation of what we said before. Okay,
so it says אין לתגר אונאה אינו בתורת אונאה שאפילו פחות מכדי
אונאה חוזר. ein letager ona'ah einu betorat ona'ah she'afillu pachot mikdei ona'ah
chozer. תני כוותיה דרב נחמן. tani kevattei deRav Nachman. So we taught
not like this second explanation but like the first one, like רב
נחמן Rav Nachman said. רבי יהודה אומר תגר אין לו אונאה מפני
שהוא בקי. Rebbi Yehuda omer tager ein lo ona'ah mipnei shehu baki.
Not because it's your livelihood and therefore we have to be more,
have more רחמנות rachmanus for you. No, you know your business. And
since you know your business, you have less of a claim that
you were cheated. Okay. Yeah, that's what we're doing. We're going back
to that explanation. Okay, מי שהוטל ידו על העליונה. mi shehutal yado
al ha'elyonah. So if the person who has the, who was cheated,
has the options... מני מתניתין? mani matnitin? Who's our משנה? mishnah? לא
רבי נתן ולא רבי יהודה נשיאה lo Rebbi Natan velo Rebbi Yehuda
Nesi'ah that we quoted before. אי רבי נתן, ei Rebbi Natan, מתניתין
קתני רצה. matnitin katani ratza. You have an option... which to do,
וברייתא, u'braisa, the ברייתא braisa we quoted at the bottom of the
previous עמוד, amud, לא קתני רצה, lo kasani ratza, you don’t have
an option. Remember רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan said it’s just you get
your money back, you don’t have an option of ביטול מקח. bitul
mekach. אי רבי יהודה נשיא, ei Rabbi Yehuda Nassi, if it’s רבי
יהודה נשיא, Rabbi Yehuda Nassi, מתניתין קתני לוקח, matnisin kasani lo'ke'ach, our
משנה mishna gives the example that the לוקח lo'ke'ach was cheated. ברייתא
קתני מוכר, braisa kasani mocher, the ברייתא braisa we quoted at the
bottom of the previous page gave the example that the מוכר mocher
was cheated. Now that’s not such a question. We’ve been all along
saying it doesn’t matter מוכר mocher or לוקח, lo'ke'ach, those are just
two illustrations. But for now, which is what the גמרא Gemara is
going to conclude, but for now the גמרא Gemara is bothered. How
come that ברייתא braisa of רבי Rabbi gave the example of the
seller having the options, and this ברייתא braisa and this משנה mishna
the option is the case is with the buyer having the options.
Okay, so let’s see what it says. אמר רבי אלעזר אונאה זו
איני יודע משניה, amar Rabbi Elazar onazu ani yode'a mishnaya, I don’t
know what to do with our משנה, mishna, whether it’s רבי Rabbi
or רבי נתן. Rabbi Nassan. רבא Rava אמר לעולם רבי נתן היא,
le'olam Rabbi Nassan hi, which is bizarre, it is רבי נתן, Rabbi
Nassan, ותני נמי בברייתא רצה. v'sani nami bivraisa ratza. And now we’re
going to modify רבי נתן. Rabbi Nassan. רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan who
before said you just can get it’s just the money back, we’re
going to modify him to say either the money back or you
can be ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. You change your mind. Yeah. Now
but רבא Rava says what should be the obvious
answer, רבא Rava לעולם רבי יהודה נשיא היא. le'olam Rabbi Yehuda Nassi
hi. No, no, no. Our משנה mishna is the רבי יהודה נשיא
Rabbi Yehuda Nassi of the previous ברייתא. braisa. ומאי דשייר במתניתין קמפרש
בברייתא. u'mai deshayer be'matnisin kameshaperesh bivraisa. Our משנה mishna gave an example
of the לוקח lo'ke'ach being cheated and the לוקח lo'ke'ach having the
options, and the ברייתא braisa gave the example of the מוכר mocher
being cheated and the מוכר mocher having the options. אמר רב אשי
דיקא נמי, amar Rav Ashi dik'na nami, that also can be inferred
from the משנה, mishna, דקתני אחד הלוקח ואחד המוכר. de'kasani echad ha'loke'ach
v'echad ha'mocher. The משנה mishna starts by saying that אונאה ona'ah applies
equally to the buyer and the seller. ומפרש ללוקח, u'mefarshei l'loke'ach, and
he gives one example, it gives the example of the buyer being
cheated, but of course it would also be true if the seller
was cheated. שמע מינה שהיא הדין למוכר, shma mina shehu hadin l'mocher,
you see, it’s giving one of the two examples. It’s not dealing
with the מוכר mocher example. שמע מינה. shma mina. Okay, that is
a good proof. Alright, we will pick up with here tomorrow and
somehow we will, I don’t know, have to just do a push.
Okay.